<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-pce-sr-bidir-path-02" ipr="trust200902"
     updates="">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="PCEP for Associated Bidirectional SR Paths">PCEP Extensions for
    Associated Bidirectional Segment Routing (SR) Paths</title>

    <author fullname="Cheng Li" initials="C." surname="Li">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>chengli13@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mach(Guoyi) Chen" initials="M." surname="Chen">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>Mach.chen@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Weiqiang Cheng" initials="W." surname="Cheng">
      <organization>China Mobile</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>chengweiqiang@chinamobile.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Rakesh Gandhi" initials="R." surname="Gandhi">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>rgandhi@cisco.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Quan Xiong" initials="Q." surname="Xiong">
      <organization>ZTE Corporation</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>xiong.quan@zte.com.cn</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="13" month="March" year="2020"/>

    <area>Routing Area</area>

    <workgroup>PCE Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Path Computation Element Communication Protocol (PCEP) provides
      mechanisms for Path Computation Elements (PCEs) to perform path
      computations in response to Path Computation Clients (PCCs) requests. 
      Segment routing (SR) leverages the source routing and tunneling paradigms.
      The Stateful PCEP extensions allow stateful control of Segment Routing 
      Traffic Engineering (TE) Paths. Furthermore, PCEP can be used for computing SR TE paths in
      the network.</t>

      <t>This document defines PCEP extensions for grouping two unidirectional
      SR Paths (one in each direction in the network) into a single
      Associated Bidirectional SR Path.  The mechanisms defined in this
      document can also be applied using a Stateful PCE for both PCE-
      Initiated and PCC-Initiated LSPs, as well as when using a Stateless PCE.</t>

      <t/>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Segment routing (SR) <xref target="RFC8402"/> leverages the source
      routing and tunneling paradigms. SR supports steering packets onto an
      explicit forwarding path at the ingress node. SR is specified for unidirectional paths.  
      However, some applications
      require bidirectional paths in SR networks, for example, in mobile
      backhaul transport networks.  The requirement for bidirectional
      SR Paths is specified in <xref target="I-D.ietf-spring-mpls-path-segment"/>.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC5440"/> describes the Path Computation Element (PCE)
      Communication Protocol (PCEP). PCEP enables the communication between a
      Path Computation Client (PCC) and a PCE, or between PCE and PCE, for the
      purpose of computation of Traffic Engineering (TE) Label Switched Paths (LSP).
      <xref target="RFC8231"/> specifies a set of extensions to PCEP to
      enable stateful control of TE LSPs within and across PCEP sessions.
      The mode of operation where LSPs are initiated from the PCE is described in <xref
      target="RFC8281"/>.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC8408"/> specifies extensions to
      the Path Computation Element Protocol (PCEP) <xref target="RFC5440"/>
      for SR networks, that allow a stateful PCE to compute and initiate SR TE
      paths, as well as a PCC to request, report or delegate them.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC8697"/> introduces a generic
      mechanism to create a grouping of LSPs which can then be used to define
      associations between a set of LSPs and/or a set of attributes,
      and is equally applicable to the active and passive modes of a Stateful PCE <xref
      target="RFC8231"/> or a stateless PCE <xref target="RFC5440"/>.</t>

      <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/> defines PCEP extensions for grouping
      two unidirectional RSVP-TE LSPs into an Associated Bidirectional LSP
      when using a Stateful PCE for both PCE-Initiated and PCC-Initiated
      LSPs as well as when using a Stateless PCE.
      It specifies the procedure for 
      'Double-sided Bidirectional LSP Association', where the PCE
      creates the association and provisions the forward LSPs at their ingress nodes. The RSVP-TE
      signals the forward LSPs to the egress nodes. Thus, both endpoints learn the
      reverse LSPs forming the bidirectional LSP association.</t>
      
      <t>This document extends the bidirectional LSP association to SR
      by specifying PCEP extensions for grouping two
      unidirectional SR Paths into a bidirectional SR Path. For bidirectional SR,
      there are use-cases such as directed BFD <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-mpls-bfd-directed"/> and SR Performance Measurement (PM) <xref
      target="I-D.gandhi-spring-twamp-srpm"/>
      those require PCC to be aware of the reverse direction SR Path.
      For such use-cases, the reverse SR Paths are also communicated 
      to the ingress nodes using the PCEP
      extensions defined in this document. This allows both endpoints to be aware of 
      the SR Paths in both directions, including their status and all other path related
      information. Associating an unidirectional SR Path with 
      a reverse direction unidirectional RSVP-TE LSP to form a bidirectional LSP and 
      vice versa, are outside the scope of this document.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Terminology">
      <t>This document makes use of the terms defined in <xref
      target="RFC8408"/>. The reader is assumed to be
      familiar with the terminology defined in <xref target="RFC5440"/>, <xref
      target="RFC8231"/>, <xref target="RFC8281"/>, <xref
      target="RFC8697"/>, and <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/>.</t>

     <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP
        14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only
        when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="PCEP Extensions">
      <t>As per <xref target="RFC8697"/>, TE LSPs are
      associated by adding them to a common association group by a PCEP peer.  
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/> uses the association
      group object  and the procedures as specified in <xref
      target="RFC8697"/> to group two unidirectional RSVP-TE LSPs. 
      Similarly, two SR Paths can also be associated using similar technique.
      This document
      extends these association mechanisms for bidirectional SR Paths. Two unidirectional SR
      Paths (one in each direction in the network) can be associated 
      together by using the association group defined in this document for PCEP messages.</t>

      <t>Note that the procedure for using the association group defined in this document is specific to the
      associated bidirectional SR Paths. The procedure for this association 
      group is different than
      the bidirectional association groups defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/> 
      for associated bidirectional RSVP-TE LSPs.</t>

      <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-sr-path-segment"/> defines a mechanism for
      communicating Path Segment Identifier (PSID) in PCEP for SR.
      The PSID is defined for SR-MPLS in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-spring-mpls-path-segment"/>. The PSID can be used for
      identifying an SR Path of an associated bidirectional SR Path. 
      The PATH-SEGMENT TLV MAY be included for each SR Path in the
      LSP object to support required use-cases. The PATH-SEGMENT TLV MUST be handled as 
      defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-sr-path-segment"/> and is not modified for 
      associated bidirectional SR Path.</t>

      <section anchor="double-sided"
               title="Double-sided Bidirectional with Reverse LSP Association Group">
      <t>For associating two unidirectional SR Paths,
        this document defines a new Association Type called 'Double-sided
        Bidirectional with Reverse LSP Association Group' for Association Group Object (Class-Value 40) as follows: <list
        style="symbols">
        <t>Association Type (TBD1 to be assigned by IANA) = Double-sided
        Bidirectional with Reverse LSP Association Group</t>
        </list></t>

        <t>Similar to RSVP-TE bidirectional LSP associations, this Association Type
        is also operator-configured in nature and statically created by the
        operator on the PCEP peers.  'Operator-configured
        Association Range' TLV (Value 29) <xref target="RFC8697"/>
        MUST NOT be sent for this Association Type, and MUST be ignored, so
	that the entire range of association ID can be used for it.</t>

       <t>The handling of the Association ID, Association Source, optional Global
        Association Source and optional Extended Association ID in this
        association are set in the same way as <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/>.</t>

        <t>A member of the 'Double-sided Bidirectional with Reverse LSP Association
        Group' can take the role of a forward or reverse direction SR Path and follow
        the similar rules defined in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/> for LSPs.</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>An SR Path (forward or reverse) cannot be part of more than
            one 'Double-sided Bidirectional with Reverse LSP Association Group'.</t>

            <t>The endpoints of the SR Paths in 'Double-sided Bidirectional with Reverse LSP Association Group' cannot be
            different.</t>
          </list></t>

        <section title="Bidirectional LSP Association Group TLV">
           <t> In 'Double-sided Bidirectional with Reverse LSP Association Group', for properties such as forward and reverse
           direction and co-routed path, it uses the
           Bidirectional LSP Association Group TLV defined in <xref
           target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/>. All fields and processing
           rules are as per <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/>.</t>
         </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="PCEP Procedures">
     <t>For a Bidirectional SR Path, an ingress PCC is aware of the forward
      direction SR Path beginning from itself to the egress PCC using the existing
      PCEP procedures. For the use-cases which require the ingress PCC 
      to be aware of the reverse direction SR Path, PCE informs the reverse SR Path to the
      ingress PCC. To achieve this, a PCInitiate message for
      the reverse SR Path is sent to the ingress PCC and a PCInitiate message
      for the forward SR Path is sent to the egress PCC (with the matching
      association group). These PCInitiate message MUST NOT trigger initiation
      of SR Paths on PCCs.</t>

     <t>The SR Path can be identified by an LSP of an SR Policy as described in 
      <xref target="I-D.barth-pce-segment-routing-policy-cp"/>.</t>

     <t>For a bidirectional LSP computation when using both direction LSPs on
      a node, the same LSP would need to be identified using 2 different
      PLSP-IDs based on the PCEP session to the ingress or the egress node. 
      Note that the PLSP-ID space is independent at each PCC, the PLSP-ID
      allocated by the egress PCC cannot be used for the LSP at the
      ingress PCC (PLSP-ID conflict may occur). As per normal PCInitiate
      operations, PCC assigns the PLSP-IDs for the local LSPs.
      Hence, when the PCE notifies an ingress PCC of the reverse LSP, it
      does so by using PCInitiate operations and sets PLSP-ID to zero and sets the
      R bit in the Bidirectional LSP Association Group TLV in the association
      object to indicate that this PCInitiate LSP is a reverse LSP. The PCC
      upon receiving the PCInitiate MUST locally assign a new PLSP-ID and it MUST
      issue a PCRpt to PCE for this LSP containing the new PLSP-ID. This
      reverse direction LSP MUST NOT be instantiated on the PCC.</t>

     <t>In other words, a given LSP will be identified by PLSP-ID A at the ingress node while it
      will be identified by PLSP-ID B at the egress node. The PCE will maintain 
      two PLSP-IDs for the same LSP. 
      For example, ingress PCC1 may report to PCE an LSP1 with
      PLSP-ID 100. Egress PCC2 may report to PCE an LSP2 with PLSP-ID 200.
      Both of these LSPs are part of a bidirectional association. When PCE
      notifies PCC1 of the reverse direction LSP2, it does so by sending a PCInitiate to PCC1 with
      PLSP-ID set to zero and R bit set in the Bidirectional LSP Association Group TLV. 
      PCC1 upon reception of this generates a new PLSP-ID
      (example PLSP-ID 300) and issues a PCRpt to PCE. Thus there would two PLSP-ID associated 
      for LSP2 (300 at PCC1 and 200 at PCC2).</t>


      <section title="PCE Initiated Associated Bidirectional SR Paths">
        <t>As specified in <xref target="RFC8697"/>,
        Associated Bidirectional SR Paths can be created by a Stateful
        PCE as shown in Figure 1.</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Stateful PCE can create and update the forward and reverse SR
            Paths independently for 'Double-sided Bidirectional with Reverse LSP
            Association Group'.</t>

            <t>Stateful PCE can establish and remove the association
            relationship on a per SR Path basis.</t>

            <t>Stateful PCE can create and update the SR Path and the
            association on a PCC via PCInitiate and PCUpd messages,
            respectively, using the procedures described in <xref
            target="RFC8697"/>.</t>

            <t>The reverse direction SR Path (LSP2(R) at node S, LSP1(R) at
             node D as shown in Figure 1) SHOULD be informed by the PCE via 
             PCInitiate message with the matching association group for 
             the use-cases which require the PCC to be aware of the reverse direction SR Path.</t>
          </list><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
                               +-----+
                               | PCE |
                               +-----+
   PCInitiate/PCUpd:           /     \       PCInitiate/PCUpd:
   Tunnel 1 (F)               /       \      Tunnel 2 (F)
   (LSP1 (F), LSP2 (R))      /         \     (LSP2 (F), LSP1 (R))
   Association #1           /           \    Association #1
                           /             \
                          v               v
                     +-----+    LSP1     +-----+
                     |  S  |------------>|  D  |
                     |     |<------------|     |
                     +-----+    LSP2     +-----+
                           <no signaling>

      Figure 1: PCE-Initiated Associated Bidirectional SR Path 
                with Forward and Reverse Direction SR Paths
           
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="PCC Initiated Associated Bidirectional SR Paths">
        <t>As specified in <xref target="RFC8697"/>,
        Associated Bidirectional SR Paths can also be created by a
        PCC as shown in Figure 2a and 2b.</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>PCC can create and update the forward SR Path and update the reverse SR Path
            independently for a 'Double-sided Bidirectional with Reverse LSP
            Association Group'.</t>

            <t>PCC cannot instantiate a reverse SR Path in a bidirectional SR Path.</t>

            <t>PCC can establish and remove the association relationship on a
            per SR Path basis.</t>

            <t>PCC MUST report the change in the association group of an SR
            Path to PCE(s) via PCRpt message.</t>

            <t>PCC can report the forward and reverse SR Paths independently
            to PCE(s) via PCRpt message.</t>

            <t>PCC can delegate the forward and reverse SR Paths independently
            to a Stateful PCE, where PCE would control the SR Paths.</t>

            <t>Stateful PCE can update the SR Paths in the 'Double-sided
            Bidirectional with Reverse LSP Association Group' via PCUpd message, using
            the procedures described in <xref target="RFC8697"/>.</t>
 
            <t>The reverse direction SR Path (LSP2(R) at node S, LSP1(R) at
            node D as shown in Figure 2b) SHOULD be informed by the PCE via 
            PCInitiate message with the matching association group for 
            the use-cases which require the PCC to be aware of the reverse direction SR Path.</t>
          </list><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
                              +-----+
                              | PCE |
                              +-----+
   Report/Delegate:           ^     ^        Report/Delegate:
   Tunnel 1 (F)              /       \       Tunnel 2 (F)
   (LSP1 (F))               /         \      (LSP2 (F))
   Association #2          /           \     Association #2
                          /             \
                         /               \
                    +-----+    LSP1     +-----+
                    |  S  |------------>|  D  |
                    |     |<------------|     |
                    +-----+    LSP2     +-----+
                          <no signaling>

 Figure 2a: Step 1: PCC-Initiated Associated Bidirectional SR 
                    Path with Forward Direction SR Paths


                              +-----+
                              | PCE |
                              +-----+
   PCUpd/PCInitiate:          /     \       PCUpd/PCInitiate:
   Tunnel 1 (F)              /       \      Tunnel 2 (F)
   (LSP1 (F), LSP2 (R))     /         \     (LSP2 (F), LSP1 (R))
   Association #2          /           \    Association #2
                          /             \
                         v               v
                    +-----+    LSP1     +-----+
                    |  S  |------------>|  D  |
                    |     |<------------|     |
                    +-----+    LSP2     +-----+
                          <no signaling>

 Figure 2b: Step 2: PCE-Updated/Initiated Associated Bidirectional SR
                    Path with Reverse Direction SR Paths

]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Stateless PCE">
        <t>As defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/>, for
        a stateless PCE, it might be useful to associate a path computation
        request to an association group, thus enabling it to associate a
        common set of configuration parameters or behaviors with the request.
        A PCC can request co-routed or non-co-routed forward and reverse
        direction paths from a stateless PCE for a bidirectional SR
        association group.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Bidirectional (B) Flag">
       <t>The Bidirectional (B) flag in Request Parameters (RP) object <xref target="RFC5440"/> and Stateful PCE Request Parameter (SRP)
       object <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-stateful-pce-gmpls"/> follow the procedure defined in <xref
       target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="State Synchronization">
       <t>During state synchronization, a PCC MUST report all the existing
       Bidirectional Association Groups to the Stateful PCE as per  <xref
       target="RFC8697"/>.
       After the state synchronization, the PCE MUST remove all
       stale Bidirectional Association Groups.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Error Handling">
       <t>The error handling as described in section 5.7 of <xref
       target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/> continue to apply.</t>

       <t>The PCEP Path Setup Type (PST) for SR is set to 'TE Path is Setup
       using Segment Routing' <xref target="RFC8408"/>.
       If a PCEP speaker receives a different PST
       value for 'Double-sided Bidirectional with Reverse LSP Association Group' and 
       it does not support; it MUST send a PCErr message with
       Error-Type = 26 (Association Error) and
       Error-Value = 'Bidirectional LSP Association - Path Setup Type
       Not Supported' defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/>.</t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Implementation Status">
      <t>[Note to the RFC Editor - remove this section before publication, as
      well as remove the reference to <xref target="RFC7942"/>.</t>

      <t>This section records the status of known implementations of the
      protocol defined by this specification at the time of posting of this
      Internet-Draft, and is based on a proposal described in <xref
      target="RFC7942"/>. The description of implementations in this section
      is intended to assist the IETF in its decision processes in progressing
      drafts to RFCs. Please note that the listing of any individual
      implementation here does not imply endorsement by the IETF. Furthermore,
      no effort has been spent to verify the information presented here that
      was supplied by IETF contributors. This is not intended as, and must not
      be construed to be, a catalog of available implementations or their
      features. Readers are advised to note that other implementations may
      exist.</t>

      <t>According to <xref target="RFC7942"/>, "this will allow reviewers and
      working groups to assign due consideration to documents that have the
      benefit of running code, which may serve as evidence of valuable
      experimentation and feedback that have made the implemented protocols
      more mature. It is up to the individual working groups to use this
      information as they see fit".</t>

      <t/>

      <section title="Huawei's Commercial Delivery">
        <t>The feature is developing based on Huawei VRP8.</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Organization: Huawei</t>

            <t>Implementation: Huawei's Commercial Delivery implementation
            based on VRP8.</t>

            <t>Description: The implementation is under development.</t>

            <t>Maturity Level: Product</t>

            <t>Contact: tanren@huawei.com</t>
          </list></t>

        <t/>
      </section>

      <section title="ZTE's Commercial Delivery">
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Organization: ZTE</t>

            <t>Implementation: ZTE's Commercial Delivery implementation based
            on Rosng v8.</t>

            <t>Description: The implementation is under development.</t>

            <t>Maturity Level: Product</t>

            <t>Contact: zhan.shuangping@zte.com.cn</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>


    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The security considerations described in <xref target="RFC5440"/>,
      <xref target="RFC8231"/>, <xref target="RFC8281"/>, and <xref
      target="RFC8408"/> apply to the extensions defined
      in this document as well.</t>

      <t>A new Association Type for the Association Object, 'Double-sided
      Bidirectional with Reverse LSP Association Group' is introduced in
      this document. Additional security considerations related to LSP
      associations due to a malicious PCEP speaker is described in <xref
      target="RFC8697"/> and apply to this Association
      Type. Hence, securing the PCEP session using Transport Layer Security
      (TLS) <xref target="RFC8253"/> is recommended.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Manage" title="Manageability Considerations">
      <t>All manageability requirements and considerations listed in <xref
      target="RFC5440"/>, <xref target="RFC8231"/>, and <xref
      target="RFC8281"/> apply to PCEP protocol extensions defined in this
      document. In addition, requirements and considerations listed in this
      section apply.</t>

      <section title="Control of Function and Policy">
        <t>The mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any control or
        policy requirements in addition to those already listed in <xref
        target="RFC5440"/>, <xref target="RFC8231"/>, and <xref
        target="RFC8281"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Information and Data Models">
        <t><xref target="RFC7420"/> describes the PCEP MIB, there are no new
        MIB Objects defined for 'Double-sided Bidirectional with Reverse LSP Association Groups'. The PCEP
        YANG module <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-yang"/> defines data model
        for Associated Bidirectional SR Paths.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Liveness Detection and Monitoring">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new liveness
        detection and monitoring requirements in addition to those already
        listed in <xref target="RFC5440"/>, <xref target="RFC8231"/>, and
        <xref target="RFC8281"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Verify Correct Operations">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new operation
        verification requirements in addition to those already listed in <xref
        target="RFC5440"/>, <xref target="RFC8231"/>, and <xref
        target="RFC8408"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Requirements On Other Protocols">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new
        requirements on other protocols.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Impact On Network Operations">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in <xref target="RFC5440"/>, <xref
        target="RFC8231"/>, and <xref target="RFC8408"/>
        also apply to PCEP extensions defined in this document.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t/>

      <section title="Association Type">
        <t>This document defines a new Association Type for the Association
        Object (Class Value 40) defined <xref target="RFC8697"/>. IANA
        is requested to make the assignment of a type for the sub-registry
        "ASSOCIATION Type" as follows:</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[   
Type    Name                                          Reference
-------------------------------------------------------------------
TBD1    Double-sided Bidirectional with Reverse       This document
        LSP Association Group 

]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

    </section>


  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5440'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8231'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8281"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8697'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pce-sr-path-segment'?>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8253"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8402'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7942'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7420'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8408'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-mpls-bfd-directed'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.gandhi-spring-twamp-srpm'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-spring-mpls-path-segment'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-yang'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-stateful-pce-gmpls'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.barth-pce-segment-routing-policy-cp'?>

    </references>

    <section title="Acknowledgments" numbered="no">
      <t>Many thanks to Marina Fizgeer, Adrian Farrel, and Andrew Stone for the detailed review of this document and providing many useful comments.</t>

    </section>


    <section title="Contributors" numbered="no">
      <t>The following people have substantially contributed to this
      document:</t>

    <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[ Dhruv Dhody
 Huawei Technologies
 Divyashree Techno Park, Whitefield
 Bangalore, Karnataka  560066
 India

 Email: dhruv.ietf@gmail.com

 Zhenbin Li
 Huawei Technologies
 Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.
 Beijing  100095
 China

 Email: lizhenbin@huawei.com


 Jie Dong
 Huawei Technologies
 Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.
 Beijing  100095
 China

 Email: jie.dong@huawei.com


]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>


  </back>
</rfc>
